<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flatiron&nbsp;school | Web Dev Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/categories/flatiron-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-29T23:42:04-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Liz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A look inside of the jQuery library]]></title>
    <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/29/a-look-inside-of-the-jquery-library/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-29T21:44:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/29/a-look-inside-of-the-jquery-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After working with jQuery a bit, I appreciate how streamlined it makes traversing and manipulating the DOM. In this post, I want to understand some of the bigger picture domain components that make it possible. We will take a look at the DOM, NodeLists, and how to implement the jQuery library in your code.</p>

<h1>A few basics</h1>

<blockquote><p>jQuery is a fast, small, and feature-rich JavaScript library. It makes things like HTML document traversal and manipulation, event handling, animation, and Ajax much simpler with an easy-to-use API that works across a multitude of browsers.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>$() is the equivalent of jQuery() - it&rsquo;s just a function</li>
<li>jQuery functions usually take one argument - either a selector or something on the document</li>
<li>jQuery is built on top of the DOM domain object model</li>
<li>placing $() around an item turns it into a jQuery object</li>
</ul>


<h2>Overview of the DOM</h2>

<p>The DOM (or Document Object Model) is a programming interface for HTML and XML documents. It provides a structured representation of the document and defines a way that the structure can be accessed so the document structure, style and content can be manipulated. The DOM provides a representation of the document as a structured group of nodes and objects that have properties and methods.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://www.w3schools.com/js/pic_htmltree.gif">http://www.w3schools.com/js/pic_htmltree.gif</a>" width="850"></p>

<p>Essentially, it connects web pages to scripts or programming languages. When a webpage loads, the browser creates a Document Object Model of the page. The tree is composed of objects!</p>

<p>Side note: The jQuery function $ and many of the jQuery methods like click and animate return a jQuery object or NodeList, which is part object and part array. A NodeList is a collection of DOM elements, which has array-like tendencies. It is missing a lot of JavaScript functionality though, such as true Array iteration and Prototypal methods.</p>

<h2>Using jQuery selectors and functions</h2>

<p>To add the jQuery library to your application, include a script tag in your HTML.</p>

<p>Option 1: Download a jQuery file and store in your application.
<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='HTML'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;script </span><span class="na">src=</span><span class="s">&quot;jquery-1.12.0.min.js&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/head&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;code&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>Option 2: Link to a file listed on a Content Delivery Network.
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/code&gt;</span>HTML
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;script </span><span class="na">src=</span><span class="s">&quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.12.0/jquery.min.js&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/head&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>The basic syntax is: <code>$(selector).action()</code></p>

<ul>
<li>A $ sign to define and access the jQuery functionality</li>
<li>A (selector) to find HTML elements</li>
<li>A jQuery action() function to be performed on selected element(s)</li>
</ul>


<p>The funtion below accepts a string containing a CSS selector, and will find DOM elements matching this selector. The second optional argument can be passed to set the context of what this should be within the inner function&rsquo;s scope.</p>

<pre><code class="Javascript">$( selector [, context ] )
</code></pre>

<p>There are a ton of jQuery function categories. We&rsquo;ve worked with the event functions like .on(), .toggle() and .change(). jQuery event functions trigger updates to the DOM based on user interaction.</p>

<pre><code class="Javascript">.hover( handlerIn, handlerOut )
</code></pre>

<p>The above funcion binds two handlers to the matched elements, to be executed when the mouse pointer enters and leaves the elements.</p>

<p>Below is shorthand for the jQuery.ready function, which will run the inner function / callback after the page loads.
<code>Javascript
$(function() {
  // Document is ready
});
</code></p>

<p>Since each jQuery function returns a modified jQuery object, you can execute a method chain. <code>$("div").animate(…).append(…);</code>, the animation happens on all of the <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements in the jQuery object, and they are all passed to the next function in the chain as part of the jQuery object. Although this is tempting, chaining many functions like can cause issues and be challenging to debug.</p>

<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve talked a big picture, here&rsquo;s a shortlist of nifty selectors you can use:</p>

<ul>
<li>$(this) : Selects the current HTML element</li>
<li>$(&ldquo;p.hello&rdquo;) : Selects all <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> elements with <code>class="hello"</code></li>
<li>$(&ldquo;p:first&rdquo;) : Selects the first <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> element</li>
<li>$(&ldquo;ul li:first&rdquo;) : Selects the first <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> element of the first <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code></li>
<li>$(&ldquo;ul li:first-child&rdquo;) : Selects the first <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> element of every <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code></li>
<li>$(&ldquo;[href]&rdquo;) : Selects all elements with an href attribute</li>
<li>$(&ldquo;a[name=&lsquo;whatever&rsquo;]&rdquo;) : Selects all <code>&lt;a&gt;</code> elements with a name attribute equal to &ldquo;whatever&rdquo;</li>
<li>$(&ldquo;a[name!=&lsquo;whatever&rsquo;]&rdquo;) : Selects all <code>&lt;a&gt;</code> elements with a name attribute NOT equal to &ldquo;whatever&rdquo;</li>
<li>$(&ldquo;:button&rdquo;)  Selects all <code>&lt;button&gt;</code> elements and <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> elements of type=&ldquo;button&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authentication with Devise]]></title>
    <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/15/authentication-with-devise/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-15T21:36:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/15/authentication-with-devise</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After building out basic authentication in class, I was curious about how to implement some of the widely used authentication plug-ins like <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise">Devise</a> and <a href="https://github.com/binarylogic/authlogic">Authologic</a>, which the RailsGuides mentioned. A ton of developers are using these plug-ins. The Devise Github page has been starred ~15,000 and forked ~3,500 times! To get a better grasp of implementing one of these solutions, I decided to walk myself through the installation and configuration of Devise using the documentation and an example applications.</p>

<h1>In a nutshell</h1>

<p>According to the Devise documentation:</p>

<blockquote><p>Devise is a flexible authentication solution for Rails based on Warden. It:</p>

<ul>
<li>Is Rack based;</li>
<li>Is a complete MVC solution based on Rails engines;</li>
<li>Allows you to have multiple models signed in at the same time;</li>
<li>Is based on a modularity concept: use only what you really need.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The Devise gem is built on top of <a href="https://github.com/hassox/warden">Warden</a>—a Rack application that runs as a separate and standalone module. Warden usually executes its role, including cookie handling and modified app behavior (hooks) for users who aren&rsquo;t logged in, before your Rails application is invoked. Once your application is running, Devise supplies helper methods, controller classes, views, models, routes, and configuration for authentication.</p>

<h3>Models can inherit up to 10 Devise modules!</h3>

<p>When you run the Devise generator, a model class and migration files are created. You can modify the configuration options (aka modules) on the model classes to determine what security features your application includes.</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Database Authenticatable:</em> checks that correct password entered, and encrypts before saving</li>
<li><em>Confirmable:</em> sends confirmation emails to verify account</li>
<li><em>Recoverable:</em> resets the user password and sends reset instructions</li>
<li><em>Registerable:</em> handles registration process, also allows users to edit and destroy their account</li>
<li><em>Rememberable:</em> remembers the user from a saved cookie, implemented with Remember Me?</li>
<li><em>Trackable:</em> tracks sign in count, timestamps and IP addresses for users</li>
<li><em>Validatable:</em> provides validations of email and password</li>
<li><em>Lockable:</em> locks an account after a specified number of failed sign-in attempts</li>
<li><em>Timeoutable:</em> expires sessions that have not been active in a specified period of time</li>
<li><em>Omniauthable:</em> adds OmniAuth support</li>
</ul>


<h3>Example: User model</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  devise :database_authenticatable, :registerable,
         :recoverable, :rememberable, :trackable, :validatable

  attr_accessible :email, :password, :password_confirmation, :remember_me, :username
end
</code></pre>

<h3>Example: User migration</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">class DeviseCreateUsers &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    create_table(:users) do |t|
      # Database authenticatable
      t.string :email,              :null =&gt; false, :default =&gt; ""
      t.string :encrypted_password, :null =&gt; false, :default =&gt; ""

      # Recoverable
      t.string   :reset_password_token
      t.datetime :reset_password_sent_at

      # Rememberable
      t.datetime :remember_created_at

      # Trackable
      t.integer  :sign_in_count, :default =&gt; 0
      t.datetime :current_sign_in_at
      t.datetime :last_sign_in_at
      t.string   :current_sign_in_ip
      t.string   :last_sign_in_ip

      t.timestamps
    end

    add_index :users, :email,                :unique =&gt; true
    add_index :users, :reset_password_token, :unique =&gt; true
end
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p><br></p>

<h1>Setting up Devise</h1>

<h3>Step 1: Add Devise to your Gemfile</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">gem 'devise' # Use Devise for user authentication
</code></pre>

<h3>Step 2: Bundle &amp; run the setup generator</h3>

<pre><code class="bash">bundle install # Fetch and install the gems
rails generate devise:install #Creates config file, etc.
</code></pre>

<p>Devise has a well commented configuration file located at config/initializers/devise.rb. This is where site-wide settings are specified. It&rsquo;s important to look over this file before creating new models or adding Devise to your existing models.</p>

<h3>Step 3: Create models (or add Devise to existing models)</h3>

<pre><code class="bash">rails generate devise MODEL #Creates model class, routes, etc.
</code></pre>

<p>Replace MODEL (could be User, Admin or anything you would like) with the class name used for the application’s users. This will create a model (if one does not exist) and configure it with default Devise modules. The generator also configures your config/routes.rb file to point to the Devise controller.</p>

<h3>Step 3: Migrate models</h3>

<pre><code class="bash">rake db:migrate # Create model table(s)
</code></pre>

<h3>Optional: Quickly create default views</h3>

<pre><code class="bash">rails generate devise:views users
</code></pre>

<p>This command creates the directory /app/views/users with all the devise views, including login form, registration form, etc. These views will help you get started, but after some time you&rsquo;ll probably want to change them.</p>

<hr />

<p><br></p>

<h1>Devise helper methods</h1>

<p>A few commonly used methods include:</p>

<ul>
<li>current_user</li>
<li>user_signed_in?</li>
<li>sign_in(@user)</li>
<li>sign_out(@user)</li>
<li>user_session</li>
<li>authenticate_user!</li>
</ul>


<p>Possible use case: Let&rsquo;s call the authenticate_user! class method (via the controller) to ensure that a user can only access certain controller actions based on their whether or not they&rsquo;re logged in.</p>

<h3>Ensure that every controller action requires a user to be logged in&hellip;</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ApplicationController &lt; ActionController::Base

  before_filter :authenticate_user!

end
</code></pre>

<h3>&hellip;except for the login and register controller actions.</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">class HomeController &lt; ApplicationController

  skip_before_filter :authenticate_user!

  def login
  end

  def register
  end

end
</code></pre>

<h2>Conclusion (kind of)</h2>

<p>The RailsGuides mention that &ldquo;75% of attacks are at the web application layer, and that out of 300 audited sites, 97% are vulnerable to attack.&rdquo; That&rsquo;s huge! The attacks can come from a variety of routes including account hijacking, bypassing of access control, presenting fraudulent content or modifying sensitive data. There are a bunch of plug-ins available, but there is no one-size fits all approach to security and your protocol should be built around the needs of your application. Once you&rsquo;re up and running, it&rsquo;s important to keep up-to-date on new authentication developments and perform regular security checks to guarantee your site is still protected.</p>

<h3>Helpful Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/security.html">RailsGuides: Security</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.rubydoc.info/github/plataformatec/devise/">Devise Documentation</a></li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://media.giphy.com/media/Z34IiLkiwSbKw/giphy.gif">https://media.giphy.com/media/Z34IiLkiwSbKw/giphy.gif</a>" width="300"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Param-arama: the Params Hash]]></title>
    <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/02/param-arama-sending-data-with-the-params-hash/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-02T20:13:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/03/02/param-arama-sending-data-with-the-params-hash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The params hash was first introduced to me with forms. When a user submitted a form in the view, a hash with that data was (magically?) passed to the controller. We later learned that the params hash can also be populated with data from the URL string. In this post, I will go over what params are, how they are passed from the view to the controller and review how to create/manipulate/accesss the params sent.</p>

<p>go over what params are, how they works and how they relate to the HTTP protocol.</p>

<h3><center>form data goes in, params hash comes out?</center></h3>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://media.giphy.com/media/x7l3pkXcDrKPm/giphy.gif">https://media.giphy.com/media/x7l3pkXcDrKPm/giphy.gif</a>" width="1928"></p>

<p><br></p>

<h1>Query String Parameters vs. POST Data</h1>

<p> After doing some digging, I discovered there are officially two types of parameters. The first type can be specified in the URL string and the other can be sent via a POST request. This is based on HTTP protocol, which handles all communication between users and databases.</p>

<p>According to the <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/v3.2.9/action_controller_overview.html">Ruby on Rails Guides website</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The first are parameters that are sent as part of the URL, called query string parameters. The query string is everything after “?” in the URL. The second type of parameter is usually referred to as POST data. This information usually comes from an HTML form which has been filled in by the user. It’s called POST data because it can only be sent as part of an HTTP POST request.</p></blockquote>

<p>In both cases, the data is passed from the user to the controller as a params hash. This happens in the Request message body for POST requests and in the Request line for GET requests. Let&rsquo;s take a quick look at what these different request types look like.</p>

<h2>Form with POST Request</h2>

<pre><code class="ruby">&lt;form action="http://foo.com" method="POST"&gt;
  &lt;input name="say" value="Abracadabra"&gt;
  &lt;input name="to" value="Gob Bluth"&gt;
  &lt;button&gt;Send Magic&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>the HTTP request would look something like this&hellip;
<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='http'><span class='line'><span class="nf">POST</span> <span class="nn">/</span> <span class="kr">HTTP</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="m">1.1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="na">Host</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="l">foo.com</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="na">Content-Type</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="l">application/x-www-form-urlencoded</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="na">Content-Length</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="l">30&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;say=Abracadabra&amp;amp;to=Gob%20Bluth
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<h2>Form with GET Request</h2>

<pre><code class="ruby">&lt;form action="http://foo.com" method="GET"&gt;
  &lt;input name="say" value="Abracadabra"&gt;
  &lt;input name="to" value="David Blaine"&gt;
  &lt;button&gt;Send Magic&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>the HTTP request would look like&hellip;
<code>http
GET /?say=Abracadabra&amp;to=David%20Blaine HTTP/1.1
Host: foo.com
</code>
So with a GET request, the user will see the data in their URL bar, but with a POST request, they cannot. This is relevant for two main reasons. First, if you&rsquo;re sending sensitive info, such as passwords, you do not want this displayed in the URL. Secondly, you want to use a POST request for large data sets because some browsers limit the length of URLs they accept.</p>

<p><br></p>

<h1>Accessing Params from the Controller</h1>

<p>When a person submits a form, the web server stores the data from the form in a request object, executes the action/method route specified in the form tag to the controller. From there, you can access and manipulate the params hash by simply typing params. Side note: The params hash is actually an instance of HashWithIndifferentAccess from Active Support. It behaves exactly like a hash, but you can access its elements using strings or symbols as keys.</p>

<h2>nested parameters</h2>

<p>Form data will be structured based on how you set up your form in the view. Hashes are created by placing the name of the nested hash between the square brackets as the name value for an input. From the controller, that bracket value will become the key to access the user&rsquo;s input e.g. params[:owner_id]. You could chain additional brackets/values after the first to create a nested tree of hashes and arrays.</p>

<p>in the view:
<code>html
  &lt;label&gt;Choose an owner:&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;% Owner.all.each do | owner | %&gt;
  &lt;input type="checkbox" name="pet[owner_id]" value="&lt;%= owner.id %&gt;" id="&lt;%= owner.id %&gt;"&gt;
  &lt;%= owner.name %&gt;
  &lt;% end %&gt;
</code>
in the controller:</p>

<p><strong>params = {&ldquo;pet&rdquo;=>{&ldquo;name&rdquo;=>&ldquo;Michael&rdquo;, &ldquo;owner_id&rdquo;=>&ldquo;1&rdquo;}}</strong></p>

<h2>array parameters</h2>

<p>To send an array of values to your controller for a given key, append empty brackets to the value attribute e.g. owner[pet_ids][]. The multiple values selected (via checkboxes or otherwise) are stored in the params hash in an array. Each items value is set by their associated HTML element tag value. You can access this array from the controller in the same way you would a string e.g. params[:owner][:pet_ids]. The ability to create these array is extremely useful, especially when it comes to mass assignment for creating or updating objects.</p>

<pre><code class="html">  &lt;label&gt;Choose the owner's pets:&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;% Pet.all.each do | pet | %&gt;
  &lt;input type="checkbox" name="owner[pet_ids][]" value="&lt;%= pet.id %&gt;" id=&lt;%= pet.id %&gt;&gt;
  &lt;%= pet.name %&gt;
  &lt;% end %&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>in the controller:</p>

<p><strong>params = {&ldquo;owner&rdquo;=>{&ldquo;name&rdquo;=>&ldquo;Sophie&rdquo;, &ldquo;pet_ids&rdquo;=>[&ldquo;1&rdquo;,&ldquo;3&rdquo;,&ldquo;5&rdquo;]}}</strong></p>

<h3>Helpful Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Guide/HTML/Forms/Sending_and_retrieving_form_data">Sending Form Data</a>, Mozilla Developer Network</li>
<li><a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/v3.2.9/action_controller_overview.html">Action Controller Overview</a>, RailsGuides</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TAP THAT...method]]></title>
    <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/tap-that-dot-dot-dot-method/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T22:37:40-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/tap-that-dot-dot-dot-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why #tap you may ask? This method made me have a ‘Ruby, you rock' moment. I first stumbled upon it during the ‘Advanced Class Methods Lab,’ which had us write methods to create new instances of a Song class, modify that instance and return it. Although my code passed the tests, it had a bad code smell. I couldn’t say what exactly was wrong, but it just felt off. I brought this up with Ian who suggested I look into the tap method. I had no idea what that was so I did a little research, refactored my code with tap and celebrated with a ‘YASSSSS.’</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://media.giphy.com/media/kGZ4jJguXT5C0/giphy.gif">https://media.giphy.com/media/kGZ4jJguXT5C0/giphy.gif</a>" width="1928">
<br></p>

<h1>What can #tap do for you?</h1>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a quick look at a before and after of my &lsquo;Advacned Class Methods Lab.&rsquo; Both sets of code get the job done. In my earlier code, there was a line for instantiating the object, then a few lines of operations on that object and then a final lines returning that same object. Another blogger aptly called this &lsquo;sandwich code.&rsquo;&lsquo; After refactoring, I could do creation, operations and return all in one line!</p>

<h3>BEFORE #tap</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">  def self.create
    song = self.new
    song.save
    song
  end

  def self.new_by_name(song_name)
    song = self.new
    song.name = song_name
    song
  end
</code></pre>

<h3>AFTER #tap</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby"> def self.create
    self.new.tap{|song| song.save}
  end

  def self.new_by_name(song_name)
    self.new.tap{|song| song.name = song_name}
  end
</code></pre>

<h3>side by side from GitHub</h3>

<p><img src="/images/tap-method/github-example.png" alt="github code" /></p>

<p><br></p>

<h1>How does #tap work though?</h1>

<p>The <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.3.0/Object.html#method-i-tap">official Ruby documentation</a> says:</p>

<blockquote><p>tap{|x|&hellip;} → obj
Yields self to the block, and then returns self. The primary purpose of this method is to “tap into” a method chain, in order to perform operations on intermediate results within the chain.</p></blockquote>

<h3>So essentially, the #tap method definition is:</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">def tap
  yield(self)  
  self  
end  
</code></pre>

<h3>and when #tap is called:</h3>

<pre><code class="ruby">an_object.tap do |object|
  # do stuff with an_object
end # ===&gt; return an_object
</code></pre>

<p>Self is the object tap is being called on (i.e. &lsquo;an_object&rsquo;). When tap runs, self first yields to the block (i.e. the code between do and end). And finally self (with block operations completed) will be returned.</p>

<h3>Going back to my Song example this would mean:</h3>

<ul>
<li>self is Song.new</li>
<li>yields to {|song| song.name = song_name} passing in Song.new</li>
<li>returns Song.new with song.name set to song_name</li>
</ul>


<p><br></p>

<h1>Using #tap to seed data</h1>

<p>Let’s go through one more example from the seed.rb file during Jeff’s CLI lecture…</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">courses = ['Math', 'Physics', 'English', 'History'].map do |course_name|
  Course.new.tap do |course|
    course.name = "#{course_name}"
    teacher = Teacher.new("Mr. #{course_name}")
    teacher.name = "Mr. #{course_name} teacher"
    course.teacher = teacher
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is more complex than the Song example, but really the purpose is the same. First, the map method goes through each item in the array with school subjects, creating a new instance of the Course object for each subject. #tap is called on each new Course object. Operations happen: A name is assigned to the Course, a new instance of the Teacher object is created and assigned as the teacher for the Course. After all that, the four new Course objects (with attributes assigned) is returned to tap, which is then returned to map. So the &lsquo;courses&rsquo; variable now equals:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">[&lt;Course:0x007f9e39047e80 @name="Math", @teacher=&lt;Teacher:0x007f9e39047db8 @name="Mr. Math teacher"&gt;&gt;, 
&lt;Course:0x007f9e39047d68 @name="Physics", @teacher=&lt;Teacher:0x007f9e39047cc8 @name="Mr. Physics teacher"&gt;&gt;, 
&lt;Course:0x007f9e39047c78 @name="English", @teacher=&lt;Teacher:0x007f9e39047bd8 @name="Mr. English teacher"&gt;&gt;, 
&lt;Course:0x007f9e39047b88 @name="History", @teacher=&lt;Teacher:0x007f9e39047ae8 @name="Mr. History teacher"&gt;&gt;]
</code></pre>

<h3>This allowed us to quickly create a ton of sample data with minimal lines of code!</h3>

<p>Takeaways: #tap is pretty awesome! It’s great for assigning properties to an object and overriding method returns. In simple cases like my Song example, it’s really just for convenience, but for more complex examples like the CLI seed file, it can actually lead to cleaner, clearer code. Watch out though, #tap should not be used to make your code look super fancy or obscure what the code is actually doing. Other interesting use cases still TBD.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://media.giphy.com/media/3oEdv5S8Th6b9gsNqM/giphy.gif">https://media.giphy.com/media/3oEdv5S8Th6b9gsNqM/giphy.gif</a>"></p>

<h1><center>damn, that sandwich can tap</center></h1>

<!-- external-url: http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.3.0/Object.html#method-i-tap


<script src="https://gist.github.com/lizkalina/7a037a413995deeb4144.js"></script> -->




<!-- 
!['yas, queen'](https://media.giphy.com/media/kGZ4jJguXT5C0/giphy.gif "yas, queen") -->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Post on Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T17:13:09-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://lizkalina.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Hello, World!&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
